Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today’s דף Daf is קיי״ג Kof Yud
Gimmel 113, the last דף Daf of סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, and we pick
up at the bottom of קיי״ב עמוד ב׳, Kof Yud Bais Amud
Bais,
and we are discussing the issue here about the range of different
things that are הקדש Hekdesh or some type of קדוש Kadosh status,
that when they’re in an עיר הנדחת, Ir Nidachas, the הלכה Halacha
is you don’t actively destroy them, but for the most part, it
seems like you bury them, or you let them rot, or you
let them die, and the question is: what is this middle status?
And there’s two basic approaches: one is that fundamentally it is obligated
to be destroyed as part of the עיר הנדחת, Ir Nidachas, but
because it’s הקדש, Hekdesh, you don’t do that type of active destruction;
and the other is that fundamentally it’s של שמים, Shel Shamayim, not
שללה, Shelalah, and therefore not obligated to be destroyed, but for some
other reason, you cannot just walk it out of the city, you
have to sort of let it rot or bury it. And the
גמרא Gemara seems to be sort of inclining more towards the first
approach. Okay, so we had said now that when it came to
תרומה, Terumah, which it says, you know, it has to rot,
that the גמרא Gemara had a discussion: are we talking about תרומה
Terumah in the hand of a כהן Kohen or תרומה Terumah in
the hand of a ישראל? Yisrael? And we concluded, the work with
is the assumption that we are talking about תרומה Terumah in the
hand of a כהן. Kohen. תרומה Terumah in the hand of a
ישראל Yisrael would be considered totally saved from the עיר הנדחת, Ir
Nidachas, and תרומה Terumah in the hand of a כהן Kohen though,
is like his own property and it fundamentally should be destroyed and
you let it rot. So let’s pick up from there. אלא אי
איתמר הכי איתמר, Ella ee itmar hachi itmar, it is one, two,
three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine lines before the lines get
wide on the bottom of קיי״ב עמוד ב׳. Kof Yud Bais Amud
Bais. אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר. Ella ee itmar hachi itmar. אמר
רב חסדא לא שנו אלא תרומה ביד כהן. Amar Rav Chisda lo
shanu ela Terumah b'yad Kohen.
When is this true that you have to let it rot? If
it’s in the hand of a כהן, Kohen, because then it’s fundamentally
his money and then fundamentally has the הלכה Halacha of עיר הנדחת.
Ir Nidachas. אבל תרומה ביד ישראל יינתנו לכהן שבעיר אחרת. Avel Terumah
b'yad Yisrael yinatnen l'Kohen she'be'ir acheres. But if it’s in the hand
of a ישראל, Yisrael, then give it to a כהן Kohen in
another city and then it’s not only is it של שמים, Shel
Shamayim, it’s not even connected to the עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachas at
all; it now belongs to somebody else, it fundamentally did not belong
to the ישראל Yisrael who was מפריש Mafresh it. And one of
the reasons the גמרא Gemara says this is because of the case
of מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, that מעשר שני Maaser Sheni you also
bury, and it assumes מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is similar to תרומה
Terumah in the hand of a כהן; Kohen; it’s something that can
be eaten, and nevertheless, you are, excuse me, not nevertheless, because it
can be eaten it fundamentally is owned by the person, it’s not
של שמים Shel Shamayim and deserving of destruction. Okay,
and nevertheless, you don’t actively destroy it, you don’t actively burn it,
but you bury it, let it rot, etc. So that now is
the governing explanation for תרומה Terumah and מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. The
תרומה Terumah is in the hand of a כהן, Kohen, the מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni is in the hand of a ישראל, Yisrael, but
both are allowed to be eaten, fundamentally deserving of destruction, but you
don’t actively burn them, you let them rot or you bury them.
Now we’re going to really explore more the idea of the מעשר
שני. Maaser Sheni. So let’s take a look.
תנן התם, Tnan hasam, we taught over there: עיסה של מעשר שני
פטורה מן החלה דברי רבי מאיר. Issa shel Maaser Sheni petura min
hachallah divrei Rabbi Meir. וחכמים מחייבין. Vachachamim mechayvin. So you have dough
of מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that
it’s exempt from חלה. Challah. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is of the
position that מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is considered ממון גבוה, Mamon Gavoah,
it belongs to God, and therefore that makes it, when the dough
becomes obligated in חלה, Challah, when you roll the dough and so
on,
it is not עריסותיכם, Arisoseichem, it’s not your dough, it is God’s.
Okay, so that’s רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
וחכמים מחייבין, Vachachamim mechayvin, the חכמים Chachamim obligate. אמר רב חסדא, Amar
Rav Chisda, says רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, מחלוקת במעשר שני בירושלים. Machlokes
b'Maaser Sheni b'Yerushalayim. We’re talking about the מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is
in ירושלים Yerushalayim and that you’re able to eat it. And even
though you’re able to eat it, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir סבר savar
מעשר שני ממון גבוה הוא, Maaser Sheni mamon gavoah hu, that it
fundamentally belongs to God, you’re eating God’s food. Okay, but it belongs
to God, and therefore that’s why you’re exempt from the חלה Challah
obligation. ורבנן סברי ממון הדיוט הוא. Verabbanan savri mamon hedyot hu. And
the rabbis figure, no, it’s your property, you just have an obligation
to eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. אבל בגבולין, Avel bigvulin, but if
it’s outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim then and you’re not allowed to eat
it, דברי הכל פטור. divrei hakol patur. Everybody agrees you’re exempt. Because
since fundamentally it is off-limits and you’re not allowed to eat it,
that would make
it, let’s assume for the reason that at that stage it would
be considered, everybody would agree it would be considered ממון גבוה. Mamon
Gavoah. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says let’s take a
look.
מתיב רב יוסף, Masiv Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef asked on
this: מעשר שני וכתבי הקדש יגנזו. Maaser Sheni vechisvei hekdesh yignazu. So
now we’re going to explore the מעשר שני Maaser Sheni aspect of
our משנה. Mishnah. Before we thought it was just like תרומה ביד
כהן, Terumah b'yad Kohen, but really it isn't. תרומה ביד כהן, Terumah
b'yad Kohen, a כהן Kohen is allowed to eat it. מעשר שני
ביד ישראל, Maaser Sheni b'yad Yisrael, you can't. You can't eat it
if you're not in ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*. So now we're going to
see how this מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni* thing really makes
sense. במה עסקינן *Bamay askeenan*? What's this case by מעשר שני maaser
sheni. *Maaser Sheni*? אילימא בירושלים *Iyleima biyerushalayim*, if you'll say it's in
ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* and then you are allowed to eat it, it
is like the תרומה terumah *Terumah* case. מי הוי ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Mi
havyi Yerushalayim*? מי הוי ירושלים Yerushalayim *Mi havyi Yerushalayim* עיר הנדחת ir
hanidachat? *Ir Hanidachas*? How could ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim* ever become an עיר
הנדחת ir hanidachat? *Ir Hanidachas*? והתניא *Vehatanya*, we turned in the ברייתא
braisa, *Braisa*, עשרה דברים נאמרו בירושלים *Asara devarim ne'emru biyerushalayim*, ten things
were said about ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*, וזו אחת מהן *Vezo achas mehen*,
and this is one of them: אינה נעשית עיר הנדחת ir hanidachat.
*Einah naasais ir hanidachas*, it can't become an עיר הנדחת ir hanidachat?
*Ir Hanidachas*. So it can't be that the מעשר שני maaser sheni,
*Maaser Sheni* is in ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim* right now. אלא ela, *Ella*,
אלא בעיר אחרת
*Ella be'ir acheres*. Okay fine, so this is מעשר שני maaser sheni.
*Maaser Sheni* in another city, ואסקוה לגבוה *V'askoah legavo*, and it had
been brought to ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* and then brought back out. But
since it had, now we're going to see why that's relevant because
we'll contrast that to never brought in. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says if that's true, קלטוה מחיצות mechitzos *Kalkituah mechitzois*, it's been absorbed,
sort of held by the walls of ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*. What that
means is once מעשר שני maaser sheni, *Maaser Sheni* is brought into
ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* and then brought back out, you're not allowed to
redeem it. You can redeem it before you ever get it there,
but once it's brought into ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*, it's like ירושלים Yerushalayim,
*Yerushalayim* claims, you know, ownership over it, claims rights to it. It's
like it's considered still in ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim* and you are not
allowed to redeem it the same way you can't redeem מעשר שני
maaser sheni. *Maaser Sheni* when it's in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*. You can't
redeem it when it's in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* and take it back
out. How is that relevant for us? Because it's relevant for us
because then if you assume that it's still like it's in ירושלים
Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*, then it's not the שלל *Shalal* of the עיר הנדחת
ir hanidachat. *Ir Hanidachas* and it's not שללה *Shallalah*. So it's completely
like not connected to the עיר הנדחת ir hanidachat.
*Ir Hanidachas*.
So okay, אלא לאו בגבולין *Ella lav bigvulin*, so it must be
that it's outside ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim* and had never been brought in
ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*. And it's מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni* like
the simple sense, מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni* in some city
that has become an עיר הנדחת ir hanidachat. *Ir Hanidachas*. וקתני יגנזו
*V'ktani yignazu*, and you see that you have to be גונז *Gones*
it. So why is that relevant?
Because if מעשר שני maaser sheni, *Maaser Sheni* out of ירושלים Yerushalayim
*Yerushalayim* like you're saying, both according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and
the חכמים *Chachamim*, is considered like it's ממון גבוה mamon gavoah. *Mamon
gavoah*, so why is it יגנזו *Yignazu*, right? Why do you have
to bury it? It should just be completely escape the הלכה halacha.
*Halacha* of עיר הנדחת ir hanidachat, *Ir Hanidachas* if fundamentally it is
מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni*, it is ממון גבוה *Mamon gavoah*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
so the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says how do you make sense of
that? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא Lo, לעולם בעיר אחרת
ואסקוה לגבוה *Lo le'olam be'ir acheres v'askoah legavo*. No, we'll say like
you were suggesting, it is now in another city, it had been
taken into ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim* and brought back to another city. So
if that's true, why is it considered to be deserving of destruction?
Because it was brought into ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* now maybe you're able
to eat it and it's considered like it's your food, you know,
especially if you don't פוסק *Pasken* like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and
therefore it is like תרומה terumah ביד כהן kohen, *Terumah beyad Kohen*,
so we get that idea. But because it is still fundamentally as
if it's in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, then it's not part of an עיר
הנדחת ir hanidachat. *Ir Hanidachas*. So why are you supposed to let
it rot? ואסקוה לגבוה הכא במאי עסקינן *V'askoah legavo hacha b'mai askinan*,
what are we talking about? Three lines from the bottom, שנטמא *Shentima*.
Okay, that it became טמא tamei, *Tamei* and that's why you have
to let it rot. Having nothing to do with עיר הנדחת ir
hanidachas. *Ir Hanidachas*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say,
so then why are we even talking about עיר הנדחת ir hanidachas.
*Ir Hanidachas*? But right now we're basically, it's טמא tamei, *Tamei* and
that's why you let it rot. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
וליפרקיה v’lifrekei, *V'lifreikei*, so why can't you redeem it? If it's not
an עיר הנדחת ir hanidachas, *Ir Hanidachas* issue and it's just an
issue of מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni* that's טמא tamei. *Tamei*,
so redeem it. Now you'll say, ah, you can't redeem it because
it's like it's still in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and you can't redeem מעשר
שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni* in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So you also can't
redeem מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni* that was in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and taken
out. But one minute, דאמר רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. *De'amar Rabbi Eliezer*,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* says מנין למעשר שני שנטמא שפודין
אותו אפילו בירושלים *Minayin lemaaser sheni shentima shepodin oso afilu biyerushalayim*. How
do you know if מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni* became טמא *Tamei* you
can redeem it even in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* where normally we assume you're
obligated to eat it and you're not allowed to redeem it? תלמוד
לומר לא lo תוכל שאתו *Talmud lomar lo suchal se'eis* when it
describes redeeming it because it's far away, it says because you cannot
carry it and bring it to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So presumably redeeming only
happens out of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. But then here's the דרשה *Drasha*, ואין
שאת אלא אכילה *V'ein se'eis ella achila*, but שאת *se'eis* doesn't have
to mean carry, it could also mean, here it says it only
means, but it could also mean eating it because you can't eat
it. דכתיב De'chsiv, *Dichsiv*, the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* says וישא משאת מאת
פניו *Vayisa mas'eis me'eis panav*, and he lifted up a gift, you
know, of food to present to them. So we're going to interpret
לא תוכל שאתו *Lo suchal se'eis*, you're not able to eat it.
So once it's טמא *Tamei* even in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* you're allowed to
redeem it and the same would be true if it was in
ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and taken out. So we still don't understand why you
let it rot. So הכא במאי עסקינן what are we talking about
בלקוח belakuach that this מעשר שני is not the original fruits of
מעשר שני. What happened was you had your original fruits of מעשר
שני, you picked all of your I don’t know olives or something,
and then you redeemed it on money. You went to ירושלים. What
are you supposed to do with the money? Buy food. You bought
food. That food, that לקוח, lakuach, purchased food, now has the קדושה
kedusha of מעשר שני. It transferred from the original to the money
to the purchased fruit. And now this food is taken out of
ירושלים and you can't redeem it because you can't redeem, you can
only redeem the original מעשר שני, not stuff that was purchased with
the money of מעשר שני. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says וליפרקיה,
I don't understand, why can't you redeem things that was purchased with
מעשר שני money? דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, הלוקח
בכסף מעשר שנטמא, halokuach bekesef maaser shenitma, top of קכ"ג עמוד א',
kuf chaf gimmel amud aleph, הלוקח בכסף מעשר שנטמא
יפדה. halokuach bekesef maaser shenitma yifdeh. So exactly our case. Something that
was purchased with money of מעשר שני that became טמא, you can
redeem it. It doesn't matter that it was purchased and not the
original. No. כרבי יהודה דאמר יקבר. kerabi Yehuda de’amar yikaver. This is
following רבי יהודה’s Rabbi Yehuda’s position that says that you have to
actually bury it. And that's what we're dealing with. You've got stuff
that was purchased with money of מעשר שני, became טמא, it's out
of ירושלים, you have to bury it. Okay. What does any of
that have to do with עיר הנדחת? ir hanidachas. Why is that
being taught in a discussion of what you do with עיר הנדחת?
ir hanidachas, So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי מאי איריא עיר
הנדחת אפילו דעלמא נמי. ei hachi mai irya ir hanidachat afilu d’alma
nami. So okay, then what? This has nothing to do with עיר
הנדחת. ir ha'nidachat. So, which you should have sort of asked from
the beginning. אלא, says גמרא, Gemara fine. לעולם בטהור. le’olam betahor. We're
talking about still about stuff that was taken in ירושלים and brought
out and it's טהור, tahor, it's not טמא. So why does it
have the status of עיר הנדחת? ir ha'nidachat It should be like
it's still in ירושלים. Because if it was never in ירושלים, then
we said never yet allowed to be eaten. That's like its ממון
גבוה. That totally gets saved from the status of עיר הנדחת. ir
ha'nidachat Because this was brought into ירושלים, it's able to be eaten.
Now maybe it's like ממון בעלים mamon be’alim and it gets the
status of עיר הנדחת. ir nidachas. But one minute. It's still like
it's in ירושלים even you brought it back out. So the גמרא
Gemara says וכגון דנפלו מחיצות. u’kegon denaflo mechitzos. Now the walls of
ירושלים fell down, meaning it was, you know, it happened all right
before, you know, the חורבן הבית Churban HaBayis or whatever, not the
חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayis, first the breaching of the walls.
And, you know, it happened on like, you know, and then that
is right at that moment of after the walls were breached and
you have this מעשר שני sitting
there. That's the special case we're talking about. So why does the
principle of as still in the walls of ירושלים not apply? וכי
דרבא, ve’chi derava, like רבא Rava teaches. דאמר רבא מחיצות לאכול דאורייתא.
de’amar Rava mechitzos le’echol de’oraisa. Okay, that you need from the תורה
Torah that the idea, you know, the idea that you have to
be within the walls of ירושלים to eat it, that's a תורה
Torah הלכה. halacha. Okay. However, לקלוט דרבנן. liklot derabanan. This idea that
once it was in the walls of ירושלים, it's still like it's
still there even you take it out, that's only a דרבנן derabanan
הלכה. halacha Okay, that really isn't true. It's not like it's still
in ירושלים. Okay, this idea that you can't redeem it and it's
like it's still there. Okay. וכי גזרו רבנן כי איתנהו למחיצה כי
ליתנהו למחיצה לא. ve’chi gazru rabanan ki isnehu lemechitza ki leisnehu lemechitza
lo. And when did the rabbis say it's like it's still in
ירושלים if the walls of ירושלים are still up? But when the
walls of ירושלים fall down, now you've got like both things about
it. It is, can be eaten or it had the ability to
be eaten because it was brought into ירושלים. So it is now
the ממון בעלים mamon be’alim and now it's outside of ירושלים. It’s
in a city and it becomes עיר הנדחת. And the city became
עיר הנדחת, that status applies to this as well. And it's not
like it's still in the walls of ירושלים because the walls fell
down. All right, very, very special case here. But at the end,
the אפשאט upshat is that the גמרא Gemara, once again is assuming
all these cases where you bury it or let it rot are
cases where fundamentally it does have the הלכה halacha. of עיר הנדחת.
Okay. If it was really מעשר שני that never brought into ירושלים,
you take it out, same way like תרומה that was never given
to a כהן, kohen take it out, no הלכה. halacha This idea
of letting it rot or burying it, it's either תרומה is in
the hand of a כהן or מעשר שני that actually was brought
ירושלים and is now able to be eaten, okay, with this special
case of that the מחיצות fell down. All right, moving on. That
was pretty complicated. כתבי הקודש יגנזו. kisvei hakodesh yiganezu. If it has
scripture in it, then you have to bury it. מתניתין דלא כרבי
אליעזר. masnisin delo kerabi Eliezer. Our משנה Mishnah is not like רבי
אליעזר. דתניא. detanya. דתניא, De'tanya, we've learned in a ברייתא, רבי אליעזר
אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, כל עיר שיש בה אפילו מזוזה אחת אינה
נעשית עיר הנדחת. kol ir sheyesh bah afilu mezuza achas eina na'asais
ir hanidachas. So here's
the idea
of like, you know, similar to the approach of there's never was
a בן סורר ומורה, ben sorer umoreh, he takes an approach that's
going to prevent there from ever being an עיר הנדחת. If there
was even one piece of holy scripture in it, one מזוזה, mezuza,
it wouldn't the whole city could not become an עיר הנדחת. Why?
שנאמר, Shene'emar, ושרפת באש את העיר ואת כל שללה כליל.
ve'sarafta va'esh es ha'ir ve'es
kol shelalah kalil. You have to burn the entire city. And since
you're not allowed to burn, you know, something like a מזוזה, mezuza,
you know, a ספר תורה, sefer Torah, things that are written on,
you know, כתבי הקודש, Kitvei Kodesh, so והיכא דאיכא מזוזה לא אפשר,
ve'heicha de'ika mezuza lo efshar, and if there's a מזוזה mezuza you
can't burn everything. דכתיב, dechtiv לא תעשון כן לה' אלהיכם. lo sa'asun
kein l'Hashem Elokeichem. You cannot destroy כתבי הקודש. Kitvei Kodesh. So rather
than saying that it is שללה ולא שלל הקדש shelalah velo shelal
hekdesh and you don't and, you know, and it gets exempt from
the הלכה halacha of עיר הנדחת, or maybe it's supposed to be
burnt but because you can't burn it you bury it, which is
sort of what our משנה mishna seems to be saying, רבי אליעזר
adopts the approach that you're obligated to burn it and you're not
allowed to burn it and therefore the whole city is exempt from
the status of עיר הנדחת. Okay, רבי שמעון אומר. Rabbi Shimon omer.
Now we get more to אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא amar Hakadosh Baruch
Hu says God, you know, this is going back like to the
midrashic statement here, which was what was it exactly, it is going
back to the משנה, mishna, אם אתם עושים דין בעיר הנדחת, im
atem osim din b'ir hanidachas, if you are able to carry out
this harsh punishment of the עיר הנדחת, מעלה אני עליכם כאילו אתם
מעלים עולה כליל לפני. ma'ala ani aleichem k'ilu atem ma'alim ola kalil
lefanai. It's like you brought a burnt offering because it says כליל.
kalil. That's at least the quote from the משנה. mishna. But let's
see what the גמרא's Gemara going to discuss. לימא בדרב אבין אמר
רבי אילעא קמיפלגי. Leima bid'Rav Avin amar Rabbi Ila'a kamifligi. So what
is this קמיפלגי? kamifligi? So what we're actually doing is leapfrogging over
רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's statement and going to the next line of
the משנה mishna where it said והייתה תל עולם, ve'hayesa tel olam,
לא תעשה גנות ופרדסין דברי רבי יוסי. lo te'aseh ganos upardaisin divrei
Rabbi Yose. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose said meaning that it should
be an eternal mound, a תל, tel, means that you can't do
anything on it, you can't even not you can't even like make
it like a garden. But רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, לא
תיבנה עוד כמות שהייתה, lo sibaneh od kemos shehayesa, it means you
cannot rebuild it as a city but you are allowed to make
it as a garden. So what is this debate? So that's what
the גמרא's Gemara going getting to. לימא בדרב אבין אמר רבי אילעא
קמיפלגי. Leima bid'Rav Avin amar Rabbi Ila'a kamifligi. Maybe they're debating this
statement of רב אבין Rav Avin in the name of רבי אילעא.
Rabbi Ila'a. דאמר רב אבין אמר רבי אילעא, Damar Rav Avin amar
Rabbi Ila'a, כל מקום שאתה מוצא כלל בעשה ופרט בלא תעשה, kol
makom she'atah motzei klal ba'aseh uferat b'lo sa'aseh, אין דנין אותו בכלל
ופרט. ein danin oso b'klal uferat. So if you have a broad
statement, a כלל, klal, in a מצות עשה mitzvas aseh and then
the לא תעשה lo sa'aseh is more specific, don't read it as
a normal כלל ופרט klal uferat and make everything be about the
limited statement, but take them actually as separate statements. So what do
we mean? It means that it says והייתה תל עולם, ve'hayesa tel
olam, it should be an eternal mound. That's a כלל. klal. It
means like completely don't do anything on it. And then it says
לא תיבנה עוד, lo sibaneh od, don't build it, don't build it
into a city. So how do we read that? Normally a כלל
ופרט klal uferat is you read it only through the lens of
the פרט. perat. If you read it that way then you'd say
both the עשה aseh and the לא תעשה lo sa'aseh are only
saying don't build it into a city. But because one is an
עשה aseh and the other is a לא תעשה, lo sa'aseh, רב
אבין Rav Avin is saying you could separate them. The עשה aseh
is leave it as a mound forever. You can't do anything. But
that's the עשה. aseh. The לא תעשה lo sa'aseh is don't build
it as a city. But you still have the עשה aseh telling
you leave it as a mound, don't do anything. All right? So
that would be the consequence of רב אבין's Rav Avin's statement. So
maybe that's the debate, that רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says
no, leave it as a total mound, emphasizes the עשה aseh which
is a broad statement, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who says only
don't build it as a city reads the עשה aseh through the
lens of the לא תעשה lo sa'aseh and the only problem is
rebuilding it as a city. So let's say that's what's going on.
So מר אית ליה דרב אבין ומר לית ליה דרב אבין, Mar
is lei d'Rav Avin umar leis lei d'Rav Avin, one holds like
him and one doesn't? לא, no. דכולי עלמא אית להו דרב אבין,
De'chulei alma is lehu d'Rav Avin, everybody can fundamentally agree like רב
אבין Rav Avin that normally you would bifurcate these and there would
be, you know, that broad statement of what do you call it,
of the עשה aseh of that leave it as a mound forever.
Okay, so if that's true, how do you get how does רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva just manage to limit it to constructing what do
you call it, constructing the city if you have the והייתה תל
עולם? ve'hayesa tel olam? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
דכולי עלמא אית להו דרב אבין והכא בהא קמיפלגי. De'chulei alma is
lehu d'Rav Avin vehacha be'ha kamifligi. Here's what they debate. מר סבר
עוד לגמרי משמע. Mar savar od legamrei mashma. When it says לא
תיבנה עוד, lo sibaneh od, it should not be built more, that
means that it doesn't just mean what do you call it, doesn't
just mean built up like a city, it just means no. building
could happen at all, nothing should be done here. So it has
to remain completely, you know, barren and you can't even make it
into a garden. מר לגמרי משמע Mar legamrei mashma ומר סבר Umar
savar עוד כמות שהיתה. od kemot shehayetah. And Rabbi Akiva says no,
לא תבנה עוד lo tibaneh od means don't build it back into
a city, you know, don't go again the way it was, not
not at all, but don't go again and build it into a
city. So what do we have? We have that Rabbi Akiva and
Rabban Gamliel are debating the לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. לא תבנה עוד
lo tibaneh od according to one means don't build it at all,
don't build it גנות ופרדסים ganot u'pardesim and according to the other
means don't restore it the way it was, don't build it back
as a city. Now what that... so that's what their debate is
about, about the לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. What it doesn't explain is
the עשה aseh because the עשה aseh still seems like it's absolute,
והיתה תל עולם. vehayetah tel olam. And if the גמרא Gemara is
saying that they all hold of Rabbi Avin, well Rabbi Avin actually
says you separate the עשה aseh from the לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh.
והעשה ve'ha'aseh remains the way it simply is in the פשט. pshat.
So Rashi tries to deal with that and somehow say okay, in
general we hold of Rabbi Avin that we don't read it as
a כלל ופרט klal u'prat but in this case somehow we take
it, we are going to assume that the לא תבנה lo tibaneh
is explaining והיתה תל עולם vehayetah tel olam and we're going to
focus on לא תבנה lo tibaneh and they're debating the parameters of
לא תבנה lo tibaneh and the word of עוד od or not.
But again, it's confusing because what Rabbi Avin's whole point was is
don't limit the עשה aseh based on the לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh.
All right, anyway, but that's what we have. I should also just
point out that Rashi suggests another reading of Rabbi Avin when he
says separate them, that rather than say there's three possibilities. One is
the classic כלל ופרט, klal u'prat, read the general statement only through
the narrow lens of the פרט. prat. Rabbi Avin is saying don't
do that. But that gives you two other possibilities. One is separate
the עשה aseh and the לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. The עשה aseh
is broad, the לא תעשה lo ta'aseh is narrow. That's one possibility
of Rabbi Avin. And Rashi suggests the second possibility, which is actually
it flips, that the עשה aseh remains broad and the לא תעשה
lo ta'aseh is interpreted through the lens of the עשה aseh and
they're both very broad. Okay, so those are the two possibilities within
Rabbi Avin. But here the גמרא Gemara, says they're debating the meaning
of the word עוד od in the לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. Okay.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Now or like אינה נבנית אבל נעשית גנות
ופרדסים. einah nivnet aval na'aset ganot u'pardesim. Now we're going to focus
in on the idea that you could maybe make it into גנות
ganot or you know into gardens according to Rabbi... Rabbi Akiva. תנו
רבנן. Tanu rabanan. היו בו אילנות תלושין אסורין. hayu bo ilanot tlushin
asurin. If there were chopped down trees forbidden, that's considered property, you
know, and that's and that's gather the property and destroy it. מחוברים
מותרין. mechubarim mutarin. If you have growing trees, then it's permissible. It
could be permissible because you know it's מחוסר תלישה, mechusar tlishah, מחוסר
קציצה. mechusar ktsitsah. It's not just gathering and burning, you'd have to
chop it down. We had that before. Or maybe you could also
say you know that's not considered to be like that's a forest,
you know, do you treat that as like property or as like
the landscape? But anyway, the first explanation is the easiest. ושל עיר
אחרת בין תלושין בין מחוברים אסור. veshel ir acheret bein tlushin bein
mechubarim asur. If it's of another city whether attached or growing it's
forbidden. Now why is that? If it belongs to another city why
is it forbidden at all? And why is it a problem if
it is growing? So מאי עיר אחרת? mai ir acheret? What is
this other city? What's this other city? אמר רב חסדא יריחו. Amar
Rav Chisda Yericho. Oh we're not talking about עיר הנדחת. We're talking
about... in עיר הנדחת it's a distinction between chopped down trees and
growing trees. The other city, the city we don't want to name,
יריחו, Yericho, which when יהושע Yehoshua conquered it he gave a curse
that whoever would rebuild it, you know, he would bury his children,
we'll see about that in the גמרא, Gemara and there, you know,
he sort of he made everything a חרם, cherem, so there it
was everything was under the ban, even... it didn't have this הלכה
of, you know, of gathering it and burning it and something that
requires chopping isn't included in it. It's just that everything was under
the ban and therefore even the trees that were growing were forbidden
to derive benefit. Okay so let's take a look. Where are we?
מאי יריחו אמר רב חסדא יריחו. mai Yericho amar Rav Chisda Yericho.
דכתיב dechativ as the פסוק pasuk says, והיתה העיר חרם להשם. vehayetah
ha'ir cherem l'Hashem. The city will be חרם cherem להשם l'Hashem under
the ban. So under the ban means like again not the special
specific more particular הלכות halachot of עיר הנדחת which could be somewhat
more limiting, but everything is forbidden. Okay, now we're going to discuss
that whole story. וישבע יהושע בעת ההיא לאמור vayshava Yehoshua ba'et hahi
lemor יהושע Yehoshua took an oath saying ארור האיש לפני השם אשר
יקום ובנה את העיר הזאת arur ha'ish lifnei Hashem asher yakum u'vanah
et ha'ir hazot את יריחו, et Yericho, בבכורו ייסדנה bivchoro yisdenah he
will lay the foundation in... with his first son, his firstborn son
will die when he lays... tries to lay the foundation if he
tries to rebuild the city ובצעירו יציב דלתיה uvits'iro yatsiv daltayah and
with his youngest son, his youngest son will die when he gets
to finally trying to put in the doors of the city. the
wall. Okay, so that's the curse. תניא, Tanya, we תנא ברייתא, tana
braisa, לא יריחו על שם עיר אחרת ולא עיר אחרת על שם
יריחו. lo Yericho al shem ir acheret velo ir acheret al shem
Yericho. Somehow we're understanding that in Joshua's curse because of the double
language ובנה את העיר הזאת את יריחו, uvana et ha'ir hazot et
Yericho, that he's talking about two curses. Anybody who rebuilds this city,
Yericho, no matter what you try to rename it, that you're under
the curse. And anybody who builds a city and names it Yericho
is also going to be under this curse. Okay, דכתיב dechativ now,
דכתיב בנה חיאל בית האלי את יריחו. dechativ bana Chiel beit ha'Eli
et Yericho. So this Chiel from the house of Eli, which רש"י
Rashi says word אלה, ala, curse, he actually went and rebuilt Yericho,
violating Joshua's ban. But we're going to understand because it says דכתיב
that he didn't build Yericho; he built a city and he called
it Yericho. באבירם בכורו ייסדה ובשגוב צעירו הציב דלתיה. Ba'Aviram bechoro yisda
uvisguv tze'iro hetziv delateha. Just like Joshua, you know, cursed. He, when
he was building, began to build it, his oldest son Aviram died,
and when he finished building it, his youngest son Segub died, Segov
died. תניא, Tanya, we תנא ברייתא, tana braisa, באבירם בכורו רשע לא
היה לו ללמוד. Ba'Aviram bechoro rasha lo haya lo lilmod. When Aviram,
his firstborn, who was a רשע, rasha, died, maybe he shouldn't have
figured out, you know, that this was Joshua's curse. Maybe should have
just realized his son was a רשע rasha and that's why he
thought his son was a רשע, rasha, that's why he died. But
בשגוב צעירו היה לו ללמוד. bishguv tze'iro haya lo lilmod. But when
his youngest son Seguv died, he should have realized this was because
of the curse of Yehoshua. So now the גמרא's Gemara saying אבירם
ושגוב מאי עבדו? Aviram uShguv mai avdu? What did they do that
you're calling, you know, this Aviram a רשע? rasha? Like, what's going
on here? How do you parse that statement you just met? So
הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, no, here's what we meant to say. באבירם
בכורו היה לו ללמוד לאותו רשע בשגוב צעירו. Ba'Aviram bechoro haya lo
lilmod le'oto rasha bishguv tze'iro. That רשע, rasha, not Aviram was the
רשע. rasha. That רשע rasha Chiel, who built the city and called
it Yericho, he should have understood why his oldest son Aviram died.
When his youngest son died, he should have then, you know, that
should have made him realize that this was all because of Joshua's
curse. Okay. ממה שנאמר באבירם בכורו איני יודע שסגוב צעירו? Mima shene'emar
ba'Aviram bechoro eini yode'a sheSeguv tze'iro? Now the גמרא's Gemara going on
to a new point. If it says Aviram his oldest, why do
you have to say Segov his youngest? מה תלמוד לומר שגוב צעירו?
Ma talmud lomar Seguv tze'iro? מלמד שהיה מקבר והולך מאבירם עד שגוב.
Melamed shehaya mekaver veholech me'Aviram ad Seguv. And which is probably the
פשט. pshat. It means that he had a lot of children in
between. It started with his firstborn and then his children kept on
dying, and when he finally finished the city, his youngest child died.
That is probably the פשט pshat of Joshua's curse and פשט pshat
of what is being described here. Okay, now we're going to tell
a story. אחאב שושביניה הוה. Achav shoshvinei hava. Ahab was like the
groomsman of this guy Chiel who built up the city and called
it Yericho. All right. And אתא איהו ואליהו למישאל בשלומה בבית טמיא.
ata ihu veEliyahu lemishal bishlomei beveit tamya. They went to when his
children died, Chiel's children died, they went to, you know, ask after
his welfare בבית טמיא beveit tamya in the house of the אבל.
avel. Interesting why the house of an אבל avel is called בית
טמיא. beit tamya. רש"י Rashi has a גרסא girsa of בית טעמא
beit ta'ama reason, because there used to be a practice that somebody
would say, what is the reason we're all here? You know, and
they would sort of talk about, recognize the the, you know, the
death and say דברי תנחומים divrei tanchumim and so on. Anyway, they
went to pay a שבעה shiva call, Eliyahu and and Ahab, you
know, who was a wicked king and they were all alive at
the same time. And the reason the גמרא is saying this is
because there's a juxtaposition of פסוקים psukim as we'll see. Okay, so
they went to pay a שבעה shiva call to this to this
Chiel. So יתיב וקאמר דילמא כי מילי דיהושע הכי לט לא יריחו
על שם יריחו ולא עיר אחרת על שם יריחו. yativ veka'amar dilma
ki milei diYehoshua hachi lat lo Yericho al shem Yericho velo ir
acheret al shem Yericho. So, you know, what's his name Chiel was
trying to figure out why his kids died. Because he didn't rebuild
Yericho according to the גמרא story. Again פשט pshat of the פסוקים
psukim is he did rebuild Yericho, but according to the גמרא, he
built another city and called it Yericho. So he is thinking why
did my kids die? And this was sounds like it was a
fulfillment of Joshua's curse. Ah, maybe his curse wasn't just about Yericho,
maybe it applied even to building another city and calling it Yericho.
Okay. אמר ליה אליהו, Amar lei Eliyahu, so Elijah said אין, in,
yes, you're right, that is what Joshua's curse was and that's why
this befell you. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so now אמר, amar,
so now you have to know who the players are. So now
Ahab is speaking up and Ahab said השתא לוטא דמשה לא קמיקיים.
Hashta luta deMoshe lo kamikayeim. I don't get it. Moses' curse did
not come true. What was Moses' curse? דכתיב וסרתם ועבדתם. dechativ vesartem
va'avadetem. stray and you'll worship other gods, וחרה אף ה' בכם, vecharah
af Hashem bachem, God will be angry at you, ועצר את השמים,
ve-atzar es hashamayim, so and you know that there won't be rain.
But ההוא גברא ahu gavra that man meaning I myself, אחאב, Achav,
אוקים ליה עבודת כוכבים על כל תלם ותלם, okim lei avodas kochavim
al kol telem va-telem, I've erected an idol on every single furrow
like in every single corner of, you know, Israel there's an eye-
there are idols that's thanks to me, says אחאב, Achav, ולא שבק
ליה מיטרא למיזל ולמסקד ליה, velo shavik lei mitra lemizal ulemisgad lei,
so and and there's been so much rain, so much rain actually
that it's flooded and I can't even go and bow down and
get to the idols. So how could it be? משה's Moshe curse
didn't come true, and the curse of יהושע, Yehoshua, that came true?
Like that doesn't make any sense. So where were we? לווטתא דיהושע
תלמידיה מקיימא? levutata de-Yehoshua talmidei mekayema? So the curse of יהושע Yehoshua
that was fulfilled, that doesn't make sense. מיד, miyad, so immediately, ויאמר
אליהו התשבי מתושבי גלעד חי ה' אלוקי ישראל אם יהיה טל ומטר,
vayomer Eliyahu ha-Tishbi mi-toshevei Gilad chai Hashem Elokei Yisrael im yihye tal
u-matar, by the name of God, you know, there shall no longer
be any rain. Now that's why we're quoting this and we made
this story because if you take a look that's from מלכים א
יז Melachim Alef Yud-Zayin and the story of חיאל Chiel building up
יריחו Yericho is also מלכים א יז Melachim Alef Yud-Zayin or טז
Tet-Zayin so we're sort of seeing these as somehow the one led
to the other. Okay, and that is and then as we know
there's a whole period of no rain in Israel. All right, חי
chai so בעי רחמי ויהבו ליה אקלידא דמטרא, baei rachamei ve-yahavu lei
aklida de-mitra, אליהו Eliyahu prayed, it's funny the word is רחמים rachamim
because it's not exactly God's רחמים, rachamim, but in heaven they handed
over to him the key to the rain and now he was
going to get to control whether it would rain or not. וקם
ואזל ve-kam ve-azal and he got up and he left. And then
ויהי דבר ה' אליו לאמור לך מזה ופנית לך קדמה ונסתרת בנחל
כרית, vayehi devar Hashem elav lemor lech mizeh u-fanisa lecha kedmah ve-nistarta
be-nachal Keris, go, you know, leave this and go eastward to this
to this wadi, והערבים מביאים לו לחם ובשר ve-ha-orvim mevi'im lo lechem
u-vasar and you know and the and the ravens would bring him
meat and flesh, you know meat and and and bread, you know
we know all of this story about אליהו Eliyahu and God appears
to him etc. ויהי אחרי הדברים האלה חלה בן האשה בעלת הבית.
vayehi acharei ha-devarim ha-eleh chalah ben ha-ishah ba-alas ha-bayis. Okay, so after
these words, you know the the what do you call it, I'm
sorry, I skipped this line. Okay, מיהיכא, mehacha, so the גמרא says
like this, מביאים לו לחם ובשר בבוקר mevi'im lo lechem u-vasar ba-boker
etc. מיהיכא mehacha where would they get the meat, you know obviously
if the ravens are bringing it they're taking it from somewhere. Where
were they taking the meat from? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב מבי
טבחי דאחאב, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav mi-bei tavchei de-Achav, from the
slaughterhouses of אחאב, Achav, okay we're tying all the players of this
together. Also אחאב Achav was the reason that אליהו Eliyahu took this
oath. Okay, so they're taking אחאב's Achav meat because he's still eating
kosher even though he's being עובד עבודה זרה oved avodah zarah and
bringing them to אליהו. Eliyahu. ויהי מקץ ימים vayehi miketz yamim it
was after, you know after the a passage of days, וייבש הנחל
vayivash ha-nachal the wadi dried up, כי לא היה גשם בארץ ki
lo hayah geshem ba-aretz there was no rain. כיון דחזא דאיכא צערא
בעלמא keivan de-chaza de-ika tsaara be-alma once God saw that there was
now too much suffering in the world as a result of this,
he had to get the rain he wanted the rain to come
back. But the problem was he had handed over the keys to
אליהו. Eliyahu. וכתיב u-chsiv so the פסוק pasuk says ויהי דבר ה'
אליו לאמור קום לך צרפתה, vayehi devar Hashem elav lemor kum lech
Tzarfasah, go to צרפת, Tzarfas, וכתיב ויהי אחרי הדברים האלה חלה בן
האשה בעלת הבית u-chsiv vayehi acharei ha-devarim ha-eleh chalah ben ha-ishah ba-alas
ha-bayis and then after these things you know the woman's child became
sick and we know אליהו Eliyahu prayed for her and the גמרא's
going to string all these stories together how that ultimately was part
of God's plan to get the keys of the rain back up
into heaven. בעי רחמי למיתן ליה אקלידא דתחיית המתים, baei rachamei le-mitan
lei aklida de-techiyas ha-meisim, so אליהו Eliyahu prayed to God that God
should now give him the power of תחיית המתים techiyas ha-meisim of
of resurrection of the dead tying back to the major theme of
חלק. Chelek. אמרי ליה amri lei they said to him, שלש מפתחות
לא נמסרו לשליח, shalosh mafteichos lo nimsru le-shaliach, there are three keys
that are you know held closely up in heaven and not given
over to anybody else. של חיה shel chayyah the one of childbirth,
של גשמים shel geshamim rain, ושל תחיית המתים ve-shel techiyas ha-meisim and
resurrection of the dead. Now what these three keys all hold together
of course is life-giving properties. יאמרו yomru now you we already gave
you the key to the rain. We're also going to give you
the key to the תחיית המתים, techiyas ha-meisim, יאמרו yomru people say
שתים ביד תלמיד ואחת ביד הרב? shtayim be-yad talmid ve-achas be-yad ha-rav?
That the student meaning you a human being can hold two of
the keys when and God is only holding onto one? לא no,
sorry אליהו, Eliyahu, if you want the key to תחיית המתים, techiyas
ha-meisim, you're going to have to give back the key of the
rain. אייתי הא ושקיל האי ayisi ha u-shakil hai give back this
the one you have and then you can take the תחיית המתים.
techiyas ha-meisim. דכתיב לך הראה אל אחאב ואתנה מטר dechsiv lech hera'eh
el Achav ve-etnah matar and that follows the next פסוק pasuk where
he is commanded to go to אחאב Achav and and God says
and I will give rain because now I God have that power
back. So it's stringing all these stories together, the story of יריחו,
Yericho, the story of אליהו Eliyahu swearing that. There won’t be rain,
then then the תחיית המתים techiyas hameisim story, and then there’s then
now God is going to bring the rain and instructing אליהו. Eliyahu.
דנחנא. De’namacha. Okay. דרש ההוא גלילאה קמיה דרב חסדא, Darsh hahu gelila
kamei d’rav chisda, so a certain Galilean, you know, expounded in front
of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, משל דאליהו למה דבר דומה. mashal d’eliyahu
l’ma davar dome. What, how can you compare this story of אליהו
Eliyahu that, you know, with the rain and the key? Okay, לגברא
דטרקיה לגליא ואבדיה למפתחא, legavra d’tarkei legalei v’avdei l’miftacha, to the guy
slammed his door, you know, and he lost the key to get
back in. Happened to me, you know, locking my keys in my
car, locking my keys in my house. Okay, so אליהו Eliyahu closed
off the rain and then he gave the key back to God,
he lost the ability to control it, God now had the ability
to control it. All right, דרש רבי יוסי בציפורי, Darsh rabi yosi
b’tzipori, Rabbi Yosi expounded in ציפורי, Tzipori, אבא אליהו, Abba Eliyahu, you
know, the master אליהו Eliyahu or my friend אליהו, Eliyahu, רש"י Rashi
says חביבי וגדולי, chavivi v’gidoli, my friend, my, you know, the great
one אליהו, Eliyahu, קפטן היה, kaptan haya, קפטן, kaptan, he’s like, he’s
somebody that’s very, you know, gets very like upset, takes offense easily
and reacts strongly. That’s what happened, you know, with, you know, in
the story that he said that he takes this immediate oath, it
won’t be any rain, he’s very insistent on it, he doesn’t want
to give it up, you know, God has to persuade him, the
whole thing. Okay, so that’s אליהו. Eliyahu. So הוי רגיל למייתי גביה.
havi ragil l’meisei gabei. So אליהו Eliyahu used to visit, you know,
was commonly would visit Rabbi Rabbi Yosi, because Rabbi Yosi even called
him my friend. איכסים מיניה תלתא יומי ולא אתא, Ichsim minei telasa
yomei v’lo asa, once he heard once Rabbi Yosi called him a
קפטן, kaptan, you know, so so אליהו Eliyahu stayed didn’t show up
for three days. כי אתא, Ki asa, when he finally came again,
אמר ליה אמאי לא אתא מר, amar lei amai lo asa mar,
why did the master not come? קפטן קרית לי, Kaptan kerisa li,
because you called me a קפטן, kaptan, you called me somebody that
like, you know, reacts and gets angry and and and gets easily
upset. אמר ליה הא דקאמרן דקא קפיד מר, Amar lei hada caman
d’ca kapid mar, he says, yeah, the evidence is in front of
us. I said it and look, you reacted and got upset. Don’t
blame me for saying that, I’m just talking the truth. Okay, end
of that story, fascinating, comparing anyway יריחו Yericho and the ban to
עיר הנדחת. ולא ידבק, V’lo yidbak, going back to the end of
the mishna, ולא ידבק בידך מאומה מן החרם, v’lo yidbak b’yadcha m’uma
min hacharem, כל זמן שרשעים בעולם חרון אף בעולם. kol zman she’rasha’im
ba’olam charon af ba’olam. It says, you know, the end of the
פסוק is, you shall nothing shall cleave to you from what’s under
the ban, you know, and you shall do this whatever and and
למען ישוב השם מחרון אפו, l’maan yashuv hashem mecharon apo, that God
should return from His fiery wrath. So okay, מאן רשעים, man rasha’im,
who are the wicked? אמר רב יוסף גנבי, Amar rav yosef ganvei,
גנבים, ganavim, which is quite fascinating. Why aren’t the wicked people that
are עובדי עבודה זרה, ovdei avoda zara, which is the whole context
here? Very strange. Okay, תנו רבנן, tano rabanan, our Rabbis taught: רשע
בא לעולם חרון בא לעולם, rasha ba la’olam charon ba la’olam, when
there’s wicked people come into the world that brings divine anger, שנאמר
בבוא רשע בא גם בוז ועם קלון חרפה. shene’emar b’vo rasha ba
gam buz v’im kalon cherpah. Okay, when the wicked person come, come
also like like shame, damnation, reproach, all that thing comes when the
wicked comes to the world. Okay, I don’t exactly see how that’s
חרון אף, charon af, but I think that they’re reading חרון אף
charon af from the word חרפה, cherpah, which means like, you know,
shame and reproach, חרון אף. charon af. Fine. רשע אבד מן העולם
טובה באה לעולם, Rasha avad min ha’olam tova ba la’olam, a רשע
rasha is lost to the world, good comes to the world, שנאמר
ובאבוד רשעים רינה, shene’emar u’v’ivud resha’im rina, with the with the destruction
of wicked is rejoicing. צדיק נפטר מן העולם, Tzadik niftar min ha’olam,
if a righteous person is, you know, passes away from the world,
רעה באה לעולם, ra’ah ba la’olam, that causes bad things to come
to the world, evil, שנאמר הצדיק אבד ואין איש שם על לב,
shene’emar hatzadik avad v’ein ish sam al lev, a righteous person is
lost and no person puts it to heart, ואנשי חסד נאספים, v’anshei
chesed ne’esafim, and men of kindness are of of goodness are gathered
in, באין מבין, ba’im m’vein, and nobody pays attention, כי מפני הרעה
נאסף הצדיק. ki m’pnei hara’ah ne’esaf hatzadik. The wicked person was gathered
in, died because of the רעה. ra’ah. So the way so that
sort of sounds like the רעה ra’ah brought it about, not the
רעה ra’ah came after his death. But what at least the way
the גמרא seems to be reading it is that
in that the צדיק tzadik died, you know, before the רעה ra’ah
came, before the evil came. Once the צדיק tzadik
dies, then evil comes. Okay. צדיק בא לעולם טובה באה לעולם, Tzadik
ba la’olam tova ba la’olam, to end on a good note, when
the righteous comes to the world, good comes to the world, שנאמר
זה ינחמנו ממעשנו ומעצבון ידינו, shene’emar ze yenachamenu mima’aseinu umitzvon yadeinu, by
נח, Noach, this one will give us relief from our consolation from
our from the toil of our hands. הדרן עלך כל ישראל יש
להם חלק לעולם הבא, Hadran alach kol yisrael yesh lahem chelek l’olam
haba, וסליקא לך מסכת סנהדרין. u’selika lach masechet sanhedrin. יישר כח, Yashar
koach, we have now finished מסכת סנהדרין. masechet sanhedrin. All the best,
see you back for מכות. Makkot.